Maheep Mahat

540-557-8604 • maheepmahat1@gmail.com • Portfolio • LinkedIn • Blacksburg, VA

SUMMARY

Full Stack Engineer with 3 years of experience in architecting and building end-to-end applications utilizing microservices architecture, Django, Spring Boot, React and Angular. Advocate for teamwork, hard/smart work and enduring curiosity.

Languages: Python, Java, JavaScript, TypeScript, C, C++, C#, PHP, SQL, HTML5, CSS3

Frameworks & Libraries: Django, Spring MVC, Spring Boot, React, Angular, Node.js, D3.js, Express.js, jQuery, Pandas **Databases and tools**: PostgreSQL, MongoDB, MySQL, H2, AWS, Kubernetes, Jenkins, Figma, Git, Maven, Docker.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

CGIT at Virginia Tech - Software Developer, Full Stack

Jan 2022 - Present

- Developed an information dashboard web app for Virginia State Police with Django, React.js, PostgreSQL, and Leaflet, to visualize accident and speeding incidents, reducing lookup time by 30 seconds.
- Improved data retrieval speed by 50% for Virginia State Police's INRIX traffic speed data using in-memory processing, denormalization, data aggregation, and data cubes; Reduced user wait time by 5 seconds.
- Created a Cron expression generator and Cron to English sentence converter for the Virginia State Police dashboard app, enhancing data precision and leading to a 30% improvement in incident response times.
- Doubled data ingestion speed for Urban Affairs & Planning department's bicycle experiment, reducing from 6 to 3 hours using pruning, partitioning, and Tuplex, improving workflow efficiency.

Mediaocean - Associate Software Engineer, Full Stack

July 2020 - Aug 2021

- Implemented a 2-step authentication via Email or Text OTP on Mediaocean's Prisma and Radia platform, slashing the document verification process by 40%, leading to expedited document approval time for clients.
- Employed cache optimization and indexing on Mediaocean's Prisma platform, significantly enhancing PDF document processing efficiency and expediting final document generation by 15%.
- Achieved a 10% reduction in deployment time by introducing automation in production releases and refining puppet modules, leading to better resource utilization and smoother operations.
- Spearheaded Server and UI development for Prisma and Radia using Java 9, Spring Boot, and React.js, boosting client engagement and satisfaction and regularly conducting Root Cause Analysis to enhance product reliability.

Siemens PLM - *Software Engineer Intern*

May 2019 - July 2019

- Refactored multiple subroutines in Polarion by employing algorithmic optimizations and reducing redundant operations, resulting in a 2 second improvement in loading of complex workflow diagrams.
- Implemented a logging tool for a Mendix application to provide real-time performance monitoring enabling the identification and analysis of system bottlenecks, which significantly aided in proactive troubleshooting.
- Developed a self-generating connector prototype for in-house microservices using the Mendix which enabled performing CRUD operations on all the microservices in the Siemens local network.

EDUCATION

Master of Science in Computer Science (GPA: 3.85/4)

Jan 2022 - Present

Virginia Tech, VA, United States of America

B Tech. Computer Engineering (GPA: 9.2/10)

Vishwakarma Institute of Technology, Pune, India

Aug 2016 - June 2020

RECENT ACHIEVEMENTS

- Awarded full scholarship of over \$113,000 (including monthly stipend) for graduate program at Virginia Tech.
- Honored with the Mediaocean Rising Star award recognizing outstanding performance and contributions.
- Received Student Achievement Award (2020) from CS Dept. at Vishwakarma Institute of Technology.

RECENT PROJECT

<u>Emotion In Motion Project</u>: Created the first and only platform for the largest psychophysiological dataset by using Coordinated Multiple Views to do temporal pattern analysis using Hidden Markov Model and Dynamic Time Warping.